这里，本不是任何人类该踏足的地方。
This is somewhere no human being was ever meant to go.
在喜马拉雅山脉的山脚深处，
Deep in the foothills of the Himalayas,
Reesei附近的气温极为极端，
temperatures near Reesei vary in the extremes,
从50°C一路骤降至冰点。
dropping from 50° C all the way down to freezing.
放眼望去，锯齿状的峭壁形成了一道道深邃而险峻的峡谷。
Everywhere you look, jagged cliff faces create these deep, dangerous canyons.
不难想象，试图在这里建造一座破纪录大桥的施工团队
You can imagine the challenge faced by crews
面临着多大的挑战。
attempting to build a record-breaking bridge here.
要进入文明地带，你必须徒步穿越尘土飞扬的山路，
To access civilization, you have to trek the dusty tracks by foot
或者乘船沿河而行。
or take a boat journey along the river.
光是抵达贾纳布大桥工地就已是一项艰巨的壮举，
Simply getting to the Janab Bridge site was an enormous undertaking,
更别说还要在这里操控建桥所需的3万吨钢铁了。
let alone maneuvering the 30,000 tons of steel necessary to build it.
没有高速公路，没有近在咫尺的工厂，更找不到一块平坦稳固的地面。
No motorways, no nearby factories, and not a flat, stable surface in sight.
这，是在大自然最严苛的环境之一中进行的建设工程。
This is construction in one of mother nature's most unforgiving environments.
这话听起来可能有点老套，但有些老套话，确实是真理。
It might sound a bit cliche, but sometimes cliches do ring true.
建造切纳布大桥，本该是不可能完成的任务。
Constructing Chennab Bridge should have been impossible.
从灼人的高温到危险的冰雪，
From searing temperatures to dangerous ice and snow,
这里的工作条件，几乎是最艰难的了。
working conditions really don't come much tougher than this.
而且遭罪的不只是工人们。
And it's not just the crews who suffer.
钢铁在极端温度下会膨胀和收缩，
When it's exposed to extreme temperatures, steel can expand and contract,
这使得加工和精准对接变得极为困难。
making it really difficult to manipulate and accurately line up.
但事实是，
But the truth is,
当工人们还在与风雪烈日搏斗时，
while crews are battling the snow and the sun, there's an even bigger challenge looming,
一个更大的挑战已悄然逼近——那就是风。
and that is the wind.
你知道吗，这条峡谷的阵风风速最高可达每小时165英里。
You see, this canyon can experience gusts of up to 165 mph.
对于在数百米高山上作业的人来说，这已经是难以置信的危险了，
Now, that's unbelievably dangerous for people working hundreds of meters up in the mountains as it is,
更何况他们
let alone
还要把数千吨钢铁精准就位。
when you consider the fact they're maneuvering thousands of tons of steel into place.
即便老天爷给你放一天假，
And even if the weather decides to take it easy on you from above,
也没法保证地震不会突然把大地震得地动山摇。
there's no guarantee an earthquake won't shake the ground to its core.
上述任何一个因素，单独拿出来
Any one of these factors in their own right
都足以让
could have put a stop
在这个位置建造峡谷跨越大桥的想法胎死腹中。
to the notion of building a canyon crossing bridge in this location.
然而，与切纳布大桥最主要的挑战相比，
And still they pale in comparison to the main challenge of Chinab Bridge,
这些都还算小意思——那就是：如何抵达工地。
actually getting to the construction site.
>> 项目刚启动时，我们受邀上去勘察，
>> When we first started the project,
他们还给我们提供了毛驴
we were invited to go up
帮助我们沿河而上。
and donkeys were provided to help us get up the stream.
>> 大卫·麦肯锡是Kovi公司的高级技术总监，
>> David McKenzie is the senior technical director for Kovi
自2004年起便参与了这个项目。
and has been involved with the project since 2004.
>> 第一次回程的时候，
>> Uh the first trip on the way out,
我们坐船走，
we took a boat on the way out cuz it was quicker by boat down the river
因为顺流而下比在那些折磨人的山道上跋涉要快得多。
than it was to try and negotiate these torturous mountain parts.
好了，这就是切纳布大桥之所以要建造的原因。
Okay, so this is why Chennab bridge is being constructed in the first place.
想象一下，你在查谟，想要去克什米尔谷地。
Imagine you're in Jammu and you want to get over to Kashmir Valley.
两地之间隔着重重大山，唯一的主要通道是44号国道，
They're separated by mountains and connected by one main artery, National Highway 44,
而它经常因积雪封路而中断。
which is regularly blocked by snow.
而这，正是切纳布大桥登场的原因。
And that's where the Chinab bridge comes in.
它只是印度一条全长169英里、全天候铁路线
It's just one impressive section of India's new 169m all weather rail line
中令人叹为观止的一段，这条铁路线可谓是穿山而过。
cuts quite literally through the mountains.
仿佛施工队面临的天气条件还不够严峻似的，
And as if the weather conditions for this construction team weren't challenging enough,
这条新线路并非人人拍手叫好。
not everyone supports this new route.
克什米尔是一个政治高度紧张的地区，
Kashmir is an area of high political tension
是世界上军事化程度最高的地区之一，
and it's one of the most militarized zones in the world,
由印度和巴基斯坦分别管辖。
divided between India and Pakistan.
>> 双方都宣称对该地区拥有主权，并各自管辖着不同的部分。
>> Both claim territory in the region and administer different parts of it.
尽管印度表示这条新的全天候铁路线将为该地区带来经济提振并改善交通联系，
While India says its new all-weather rail line will give the area an economic boost and improve travel connections,
但反对者认为，它不过是加强对该地区控制的一种手段。
opponents claim it's being used as a way of exerting more control over the region.
但尽管争议不断，这条铁路线的建设工作仍在强力推进。
But despite these concerns, construction of the line has plowed on.
整个项目共有多达943座桥梁
All in all, this thing features an incredible 943 bridges
和36条隧道，
and 36 tunnels,
其中一条隧道长达7英里。
one of which is 7 mi long.
据各方综合报道，
And apparently allin reports
这一切的总造价据称仅为50亿美元。
suggest that it's going to cost a mere $5 billion.
为了给大家一个参照，
Now, for context on that,
50亿美元在纽约只够建
in New York, $5 billion would get you
2英里的第二大道地铁。
2 miles of Second Avenue subway.
当我们审视的每个项目
Now, when seemingly every project
动辄就要花费数百万乃至数十亿美元时，
we look at costs millions, if not billions of dollars,
很容易就会对这些天文数字失去直觉。
it's easy to lose perspective over the scale of money that's being talked about.
一栋摩天大楼20亿，
$2 billion on a skyscraper here,
一条铁路100亿，
$10 billion on a railway over there,
而有些项目的花费甚至高达万亿级别。
and sometimes these projects can run into the trillions.
要平衡这些账本，换了大多数人恐怕早就吓出一身冷汗了。
Balancing those checkbooks would bring most of us out in a cold sweat.
说实话，光是想想我都有点犯恶心。
In fact, I feel a bit sick just thinking about it.
但如果你想告别头疼的财务管理，那就试试ODU吧——
But if you want to say goodbye to headaches,
这是一个一体化的企业管理平台，
then say hello to ODU, an all-in-one business management platform
提供超过45款应用，帮你把生意做得井井有条。
providing more than 45 apps to help you stay on top of business.
ODO的财务管理应用以易用性为核心，
ODO's accounting app designed with accessibility at heart
它不仅能让你放心，确保资金得到妥善处理，
not only offers peace of mind that your money is being processed properly,
还能帮你大幅砍掉繁琐的工作。
it also cuts the faf.
你可以在几秒钟内创建无限张发票。
You can create unlimited invoices in seconds.
只需绑定银行账户，
Then by syncing your bank accounts,
ODU便会自动监控付款情况，
ODU monitors payments
甚至会向迟付款方自动发送催款提醒。
and even sends automatic follow-ups to late payers.
智能AI能自动识别供应商发票数据，进一步大幅减少你的手动操作。
Smart AI recognizes supply invoice data, further slashing your manual tasks.
你还可以通过直观的数据看板，比以往任何时候都更轻松地追踪财务数据。
And you even get access to intuitive dashboards to make tracking your financial data easier than ever.
而且你在哪里都没关系。
It doesn't matter where you are either.
这款应用会自动适配当地的税务法规，帮你保持合规守法。
The app caters to your local tax regulations, helping to keep you compliant and law-abiding.
但有个问题——那就是：根本没有问题。
But here's the catch. There isn't one.
ODO将让你免费试用他们的财务管理应用。
ODO will let you try out their accounting app for free.
而且有无限的托管和支持，
And with unlimited hosting and support,
你没有理由不去试试ODO的第一款应用——完全免费。
you can't really go wrong to try your first ODO app for free.
点击简介里的链接即可。
Head to the link in the description.
当你们花时间去看我们的视频赞助商时，
It massively helps us out here at the B1M
对我们B1M来说真的帮助很大。
when you guys take the time to go and check out our video sponsors.
所以，请在视频结束后去看看。
So, please do do that at the end of the video.
好了，从管理你的钱财，
Now, from managing your money
到管理喜马拉雅山脉中的一座超级大桥，
to managing a mega bridge in the Himalayas,
让我们回到切纳布的故事。
let's get back to Chinab.
这是2020年切纳布大桥的施工现场。
This is the Chennab Bridge work site in 2020.
在峡谷两侧，你会发现这些加工车间。
And on either side of the canyon, you'll notice these fabrication workshops.
在现代建设工地上，这种车间并不常见。
You wouldn't usually find them on modern construction sites.
通常，像这种规模的项目，
Usually on a project this big,
关键构件会在远方的工厂预制好，
key components would be pre-fabricated in factories far away
再运到工地。
and then maneuvered to sight.
但正如我们提到的，这里根本行不通。
But as we mentioned, that wasn't an option here.
所以，现在你大概在问自己：
So, right about now, you're probably asking yourself,
既然这个工地如此难以抵达，
well, if this project's so hard to get to,
他们到底是怎么把3万吨钢铁运上去的？
then how the hell did they get 30,000 tons of steel up there?
而这个答案，着实令人叹为观止。
And the answer is pretty extraordinary.
光是让这个极端的地点变得勉强可以进入，
just to make this extraordinary location even remotely accessible.
他们就专门为这个项目铺设了26公里的道路。
They put in 26 km worth of roads just for this project.
但如果你容易晕车，
But if you're prone to travel sickness,
我劝你现在就别看了——因为这些道路建在一些相当惊险的位置，
I'd advise you look away now because these roads were built in some pretty precarious locations,
紧贴着山体，沿着一些令人心惊胆战的悬崖边缘延伸。
clinging to the side of mountains and going along some serious cliff edges.
>> 运输钢铁最高效的方式是以平板形式运输。
>> The most efficient way of transporting steel is in flat plate.
把它想象成一份宜家目录。
Think of it as an IKEA catalog.
所有东西都以平装
Everything came to sight flat
形式运抵工地，
packed and indeed all the cutting
所有的切割和钻孔工作都在现场完成。
and all the drilling was done on site.
>> 而当你好不容易抵达工地后，也别指望事情会容易多少。
>> And don't expect things to get much easier when you've reached the site.
一旦所有材料终于就位，
Once you finally have all the materials on location,
接下来就是那件"小事"——
then comes the small issue of building the bridge
在数百米高空的巨大峡谷上建桥。
hundreds of meters above the ground over a massive canyon.
这里的地形，简直就是噩梦。
The topography here is nothing short of a nightmare.
一条被河流切割的锯齿状岩石峡谷，
A jagged rocky canyon
景色固然壮美，
split by a river makes for some beautiful views,
却是一项极为棘手的工程挑战。
but an incredibly tricky engineering job.
正如我之前提到的，最大的挑战
As I mentioned earlier, one of the biggest factors
之一是风，
is the wind,
这要归因于一种被称为文丘里效应的现象。
thanks to a phenomenon known as the Venturi effect.
就是当一条狭窄的通道（比如峡谷）实际上变成了一个巨大的漏斗。
That's when a narrow passage like a canyon effectively becomes a giant funnel.
当风穿过时，
As wind passes through,
随着风速加快，其压力下降，
its pressure drops as its speed increases,
产生强大而混乱的气流模式。
creating powerful and chaotic patterns.
而这一切，还没算上我们尚未谈到的地形因素。
And that's all before we've discussed the terrain.
从地质学角度来看，喜马拉雅山脉非常年轻，至今仍在运动之中。
In geological terms, the Himalayas are very young and they're still moving.
这条山脉是由
The range was forced up
印度板块与欧亚板块碰撞挤压而形成的，
by the Indian and Eurasian plates driving into each other,
造就了一片地形极为扭曲的土地。
creating a heavily twisted landscape.
沿峡谷分布的岩石既破碎又松脆。
The rock along its canyons is fractured and fryable.
从本质上讲，峡谷大致呈V形。
Now, by nature, a canyon is kind of a V-shape.
而问题在于，
And the problem is,
如果将一座塔墩固定在这个V形的一侧——
if you fix a tower to one side of that V-shape,
尤其是岩石条件极不稳定的一侧——
particularly one side that's got very unstable rock conditions,
那座塔墩就会有向谷底滑落的倾向。
there's a tendency for that tower to want to slide down the valley and slip.
这就是为什么切纳布大桥采用拱形设计。
Which is why the Chennap Bridge is an arch design.
从两端各自起建，
It starts from either end
两侧在中间汇合，
and both sides meet in the middle,
形成这样一个锁合结构。
creating a locked formation like this.
当两侧在中间相遇时，
As they meet in the middle,
彼此相互推压，
the two sides push against each other
将重量沿拱脚向下传递到山体两侧。
and force their weight down their legs into the sides of the mountain.
我提到过，峡谷有点像一个风漏斗，会产生这些强劲的阵风模式。
So, I mentioned that a canyon acts a bit like a wind funnel, creating these powerful gust patterns.
通常，你会建造一个结构模型——
Usually, you'd create a model of the structure,
在这个案例中就是大桥模型——
in this case a bridge,
然后将其缩小版放入风洞中进行测试。
and then put a scaled down version of it to the test in a wind tunnel.
虽然这里确实
And while that was done here
做了约1:50的缩比模型测试，
with about a 1 to 50 scale model,
但独特的地形还是需要更深入的研究。
the unique topography called for some more drastic research.
>> 我们随后进行了一些局部测试，包括物理测试和计算机仿真测试。
What we then did was some uh localized tests, both physical tests, but also computational tests.
>> 我们对周围的环境进行了建模，包括所有的山丘和山谷。
So we model the environment around it, all the hills, the valleys.
>> 这样我们就能计算出
So then we could actually then calculate
局部的加速气流——
what are the accelerated flows locally
因为它们当然会提升整体风速。
because of course they push up the net wind speed.
>> 比如说风速加速了20%，
So there's an acceleration of 20%,
你原本最高50
your maximum wind speed of say 50
m/s的风速现在就变成了60到70 m/s。
m/s is now 60 70 m/s.
>> 所以你必须将这些因素都纳入考量，
So you've got to take those things into account
而这里所做的重要工作，
and that's the important thing was done here
就是进行了这些特定的研究，因为它们对设计至关重要。
was to do those particular studies because they were very important to the design.
>> 能用一个无比强劲的拱来
>> Now the ability to stabilize this bridge with an incredibly strong arch
稳固这座大桥至关重要，
is crucial
但它横跨的峡谷距下方的河流有数百米之高。
but it's stretching over a canyon hundreds of meters above the river down below.
要真正建造它，工人们必须首先搭建一座缆索起重机。
To actually build it, crews had to first construct a cable crane.
有点像高空走钢丝，或者一条由缆索构成的单轨道。
It's a bit like an aerial trapze or a monorail made of cables.
在峡谷两侧分别建造塔架，再用缆索将它们连接起来。
Towers are constructed on either side of the canyon and a cable connects them.
拱桥的钢铁构件通过缆索起重机被牵引到正确的位置。
Pieces of steel for the arch are winched across on the cable crane into their correct location.
拱桥的每一侧都从底部向上建造，
Each side of the arch is then built from the bottom upwards,
由锚入岩石的缆索拉住，
held back by cables that are locked into the rock
防止整体坠入下方近400米处的河流。
to stop it all from falling nearly 400 m down into the river below.
大功告成，一座拱桥就这样诞生了。
And once complete, hey presto, you've got an arch.
拱桥是支撑整个桥体结构的核心构件。
Now, the arch is the key component supporting the entire bridge structure.
但显然，火车现在还不能直接在上面通行。
But obviously, it's not fit for a train to go across it just yet.
一旦支撑塔架竖立起来，
Once the supporting towers are erected,
顶部桥面板就要开始发挥作用了，
that's when the top deck comes into play,
而这可是个相当重的部件。
and it's a pretty heavy components.
桥面板是大桥平坦部分的结构，分段建造。
The top deck is a flat piece of the bridge that's constructed in sections.
基本上，从峡谷两侧各自出发，依次铺设一块桥面板。
Basically, working from each side of the canyon, a piece of the bridge deck is laid.
然后在它后面再放一块，再后面再放一块，
Then another piece is put in behind it,
如此循环，桥面板逐渐向峡谷中间延伸推进，
then another piece behind that,
直到两侧在中间汇合。
and so on and so on,
and gradually the bridge deck is pushed out across the canyon until the two sides meet in the middle.
这就是所谓的顶推法。
It's what's known as a launch methodology.
令人欣喜的是，这座结构规模如此之大，
What's cool is that this structure is so big
使得这一地区通常经历的地震，
that the scale of earthquakes generally experienced here
对它来说影响相对较小。
shouldn't be too much of an issue for it in comparison.
但这不仅仅是运气使然。
But that's more than just a stroke of luck.
这里的工程师们很清楚，该地区面临着相当剧烈的地震活动。
Engineers here were well aware this area faces some pretty intense seismic activity.
>> 当桥梁达到这种规模时，
>> When you get bridges of this size,
奇妙的是，想象一下地面在晃动，
curiously, if you imagine the ground is shaking,
但相对于结构的尺寸和跨度
but in proportion to the size and span of the structure,
来说，这种晃动其实相当小。
that shaking is actually quite small.
>> 如果相对跨度
If you have the span relatively
而言晃动量是两倍，
that shaking is twice as much
那是因为晃动量本身是一个固定数值。
because the shaking is a fixed amount.
>> 比方说地面晃动正负10厘米。
So the ground shakes by let's say plus or minus 10 cm.
>> 但如果桥长100米，
But if the bridge is 100 m long
加倍到200米，
if you double it to 200 m long
那相对影响自然就会减小。
of course then the relative effect diminishes.
>> 所以实际上，地震对主拱的影响较小，
So actually the seismic is less of an impact on the main arch
但它确实会影响
but it does affect
所有其他引桥结构。
all the rest of the approach structures.
>> 不用说，顶部桥面板的稳定性至关重要。
>> It goes without saying the stability of the top deck is crucial.
>> 列车的安全必须是项目建设的核心。
The safety of trains has to be central to the project's construction.
而威胁大桥稳定性的主要环境因素之一，
And one of the key environmental threats to the bridge's stability
是全球各地都会遭遇的——
is one that is experienced around the world,
尽管在英国也许感受没那么深——
although maybe less so in the UK.
那就是阳光。
The sunshine.
如果你之前有在认真听，
If you were paying attention,
你会记得我在视频开头就说过，
you remember I said right at the start of this video
切纳布大桥所在地的气温
that temperatures at Chinab Bridge vary from freezing
从冰点到骄阳下的50°C不等。
all the way up to a scorching 50° C.
而这会影响大桥拱桥所用的钢铁。
And that impacts the steel that the bridge arch is made of.
峡谷最大的问题
The big problem with a canyon
在于，太阳在任何时候都只能照射到大桥的局部区域，
is that the sun can only shine on sections of the bridge
这意味着各部分将在不同温度下运行。
at any one time, meaning it'll need to operate at different temperatures.
随着桥拱的升温和降温，
Now, as the bridge arch warms and cools,
它会弯曲和形变，
it bends and flexes,
这对行驶中的列车来说可不是好事。
which isn't great for moving trains.
但为了解决这个问题，钢轨采用了预应力处理。
But to get around that, the rails have been pre-stressed.
它们被拉得非常紧绷，以保持稳定。
They've been pulled really tight for stability.
与此同时，它们还能在桥上的固定扣件中自由移动。
They're also allowed to move freely of their fixings on the bridge.
也就是说，桥上的扣件
So, the fixings that are on the bridge
将钢轨托住，
have the rails sitting in them,
但并没有将其固定死。
but they're not actually attached.
这样，随着大桥随时间推移而运动，钢轨也能前后自由伸缩。
So the rails can move back and forth as the bridge moves over time.
由芬兰WSP团队设计，
Designed by the WSP team in Finland,
拱桥及其塔架巍然耸立于切纳布河之上。
the arch and its towers loom over Chinab River.
岩石与钢铁和山峦背景融为一体，
The rock and steel blend in with the mountainous backdrop
也因此为乘客带来了地球上最壮美的列车观景体验之一。
and in doing so offer some of the best train passenger views on the planet.
>> 是的，我非常幸运，
>> Yeah, I've been fortunate, very fortunate
有幸在我的职业生涯中参与了许多令人振奋的结构工程项目。
to work on a number of very exciting structures in my lifetime.
>> 但这一个对我尤为特别，
Um, but this one holds particular passion for me
因为我从零开始亲眼见证了它20年的建造历程，
because it's having seen it from ground up over a 20-year period,
看到了它是在哪里建起来的，
having seen, you know, where it's been built,
>> 以及它的建造质量——
quality with which it's been built as well,
它在现场被建造得如此精良，
it's incredible how well it's been fabricated in in the yard
真的是一件令人难以置信的工程杰作。
really is an incredible piece of engineering.
>> 我想，就这样看着它的照片——
And I think just looking at the pictures
就像我现在看着屏幕上这些一样——
as I am on my screen in front of me,
它真的触动了我内心深处，
it really does target the heart springs as being, you know,
它是我最感兴趣的挑战。
the ch the challenge I am most interested in.
>> 证据就是，我每天都把它放在笔记本电脑上看。
The proof is I have it on my laptop every day
to look at it.
这条铁路线于去年夏天正式通车，
The line was inaugurated in summer last year,
标志着印度互联互通新篇章的开启。
as India begins its next chapter of connectivity.
而切纳布大桥只是印度众多铁路项目中的一个，
And while Chennab bridge is just one part of a number of rail projects
但它或许是其中最令人叹为观止的。
across this country, it might be the most impressive.
[snorts] 为了建造这座大桥，
[snorts] To create this bridge,
施工团队不得不在前人从未踏足的地方开疆辟土。
construction teams had to build where no one else has built before.
然而，凭借坚定的意志和勇于创新，他们将它变成了现实。
And yet, through determination and innovation, they've made it a reality.
在施工首次开始的20多年后，历经重重延误和复杂状况，
More than 20 years after construction first began,
经历了乘船、骑驴穿越山路，
following delays and complications, boat journeys, and trekking on donkeys,
以及缆索起重机的辅助和数英里的专建道路，
cable cranes, and miles of purpose-built roads,
施工团队找到了解决之道。
construction crews found a way.
切纳布大桥是
The Chennad Bridge is a perfect example of the hardships
建设团队在我们星球一些最非凡环境中作业时所面临艰辛的完美见证。
faced by construction teams working in some of our planet's most extraordinary environments.
为建造这样的结构所投入的巨大努力，
The enormous effort invested to create structures like this
为后代铺平了道路，
paves the way for future generations
也再一次证明了令人叹为观止的建筑行业所具备的能量。
and proves once again what the amazing construction industry is capable of.
本视频由ODU赞助。
This video was sponsored by ODU.
衷心感谢他们一直以来的支持。
Want to say a huge thank you to them for their support.
请点击链接，
Please do click the link,
进一步了解ODO，
go and find out more about ODO
加入这个出色的平台。
and get involved in what is a fantastic platform.
一如既往，如果你喜欢这个视频，
And as always guys, if you enjoyed this video
想从这个权威建筑视频频道获取更多内容，
and you want to get more from the definitive video channel for construction,
请点击订阅按钮。
hit that subscribe button.